<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>circularspace</title><link href="https://mindriot101.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://mindriot101.github.io/feeds/gaming.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://mindriot101.github.io/</id><updated>2013-12-09T23:23:34+00:00</updated><entry><title>Dickwraith stories</title><link href="https://mindriot101.github.io/blog/2013/12/09/dickwraith-stories/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-12-09T23:23:34+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon Walker</name></author><id>tag:mindriot101.github.io,2013-12-09:blog/2013/12/09/dickwraith-stories/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I've done some very dickish things as a darkwraith in Dark Souls, mostly involving firestorm. I'm certain my stories are not the &lt;em&gt;worst&lt;/em&gt; but they're probably some of the worst things &lt;em&gt;I've&lt;/em&gt; done! I'm leaving this here as a confessional of sorts, but also a great place to leave my invasion stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some context: these stories were probably performed on my SL1 dickwraith character, using a +5 chaos battle axe for max damage. I'm armed with a max pyro flame with firestorm and fire surge for the comedy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was fighting a naked character with bonewheel shield, and fighting on the roof of Sen's. We were on the narrow bridge and my opponent was clearly trying to run past me to the boss fog. We had a small interaction which left me with the impression that it would only take two hits, and even hitting the bonewheel shield would do considerable damage. The single hit I landed caused fear in my opponent so she started running. I thought of getting a handy backstab (remember I'm playing a dickwraith) so pursued. In my excitement I didn't notice that she went into the cage lift and I continued running. We shared a tense ride down to the ground floor, and we were both attacking like mad. My wolf ring allowed me to get the hits and my victory achieved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again on the roof of Sen's, I enter the host's world and go on the hunt. I see the archer is missing so start running to the top. I see the words "Summoning Phantom" on my screen and realising that Tarkus was on his way. I'd earlier failed to kill a character being assisted by Tarkus that night so thought I was in for a difficult fight. I got to the top expecting Tarkus and the host but saw neither, until I glanced across to the building with Tarkus' summon sign and saw them both standing in the doorway. They had not seen me yet so I armed firestorm and waited out of sight until the inevitable: they started crossing the bridge. When the host neared I cast firestorm and caught him as he rounded the corner, probably expecting a quick backstab on the black phantom crouching on the floor just before flames erupted out from the ground.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="dark souls"></category></entry><entry><title>Dark Souls magic</title><link href="https://mindriot101.github.io/blog/2013/03/15/dark-souls-magic/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-03-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Simon Walker</name></author><id>tag:mindriot101.github.io,2013-03-15:blog/2013/03/15/dark-souls-magic/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was sceptical when I first stepped into the land of Lordran and perished at the hands of yet
another undead nightmare hunting me, for I assume I'd angered it in some way. I do not know what I
did to annoy this poor hollowed creature but it wanted my blood so I unburdened it of the strange
life force causing it to attack me so. I had already died to it many times but this time I managed
to vanquish the foe and move on...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...to the next foe and subsequently die at its cold hands. This pattern repeated itself for quite a
while until finally I managed to defeat the Asylum Demon and escape that wretched place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="darksouls" src="{{" title="site.url }}/assets/images/darksouls.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was something magical about that experience that, now that I've finished the game a few times,
I thought I'd never get back. Something part encouraging, like making progress in a puzzle; and part
infuriating, repeating the same part over and over again, but I knew that the game was not at fault.
It was me, I had to change my approach. Maybe switch out my equipment or take things slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great design of the game which I'm sure is deliberate is preying on human nature where, for
example in video games, we encounter something difficult, only to fail at completing the task; we
rush in recklessly only to fail again. The more we try the more frustrated we become and the worse
we play.  Dark Souls forces you to take a few minutes, calm down and &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; about the situation: is
rushing in head on really the best solution, maybe I should draw the enemies closer to me one at a
time and pick them off, maybe I should get my bow out and snipe, wearing the group down until I can
pass through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is compounded by the bonfire system which respawns every&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; enemy and forces us to improve our
play. We will not get any better by "saving" our progress at the nearest bonfire. My favourite
example of this is the spell system. You have only a limited number of casts. To get more you need
to rest at the bonfire, but this will respawn the enemies so you have to learn to &lt;em&gt;be more
efficient&lt;/em&gt; with your spells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of my spell of playing the game I was getting complacent. I knew the
enemies well and could predict their actions. I would still die to the stupidest things, or
unfortunate circumstances, I was not &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt; at the game, just sufficient, but I felt strong.
Worthy of defeating this game widely acknowledged for its difficulty. I had lost the magic that I
felt at first when I played it many months ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then I took a break. Not deliberately: other games came and went, and other commitments had to
take priority. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months went by and I got curious. Could I still play the game as well as I used to? Is it like
riding a bike - once you learn you never lose the knack?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suck again, dying to the first few hollows I encountered. I'm currently stuck again at the Parish
and that feeling of inadequacy is rushing back to me, where the game is most magical. If there's no
challenge to overcome then are you really playing the right game?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've started watching speed runs of the game and this seems an amazing way to keep the PvE section
of the game new and fresh. I delight in telling people that my first playthrough took around 50
hours, and some people can complete it in less than 1. PvP is the other way to sustain this game for
players: generally being a dick and invading poor helpless beginners in Anor Londo (more likely
someone in dark Anor Londo just waiting for fresh meat, or someone on NG+), the PvP arenas in the
Township, or invading in common PvP zones. For a game with no communication beyond predetermined
messages and gestures it's surprisingly easy to convey emotion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I genuinely believe that Dark Souls is one of the best games I've played, with amazing amounts of
depth if you search for it. Check out &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL4825DBA198EBE9B9"&gt;EpicNameBro's amazing lore series&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLWLedd0Zw3c5RCXboUsPwHsZJlXB2CzCz"&gt;VaatiVidya's Prepare To Cry series&lt;/a&gt; for lore discussion, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/UberGusMage/videos?flow=grid=0"&gt;UberGoose's speedrunning&lt;/a&gt; to see just how much possibility there is for extending the game. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The depth to the character build system is immense, the range of techniques that you can employ are
diverse and always fun. Create a sorcerer only build, using magic only. Or set yourself some
challenges like (my current build) a no-shield run&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This will teach yourself to dodge
effectively as endorsed by &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/vageta311"&gt;Vageta311&lt;/a&gt;, check out his amazing
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL5CC8A65E1E0EB80D"&gt;Everything possible before the gargoyles&lt;/a&gt;
series for a real eye-opener to the game and just how much is possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively take a break for a few months. Let your ability die down and regain that magic for
yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;nearly&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;probably not wise to challenge myself after such a long break in my playing&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="dark souls"></category></entry></feed>